<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" ?>

<casaxml xmlns="http://casa.nrao.edu/schema/psetTypes.html"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://casa.nrao.edu/schema/casa.xsd
file:///opt/casa/code/xmlcasa/xml/casa.xsd">

<task type="function" name="polconvert" category="analysis">

  <shortdescription>\n\nVersion 1.2-r13\n\nConverts VLBI visibilities from mixed-polarization basis (i.e.,\nlinear-to-circular) into circular basis. Works with single VLBI stations \nas well as with phased arrays (i.e., phased ALMA).\n\n</shortdescription>
      
       <description>\n\nVersion 1.2-r13\n\nConverts VLBI visibilities from mixed-polarization basis (i.e.,\nlinear-to-circular) into circular basis. Works with single VLBI stations \nas well as with phased arrays (i.e., phased ALMA).\n\n</description>


<input>

    <param type="string" name="IDI" mustexist="true">
      <description>Input FITS-IDI file with VLBI visibilities. It can \nalso be a direcotry containing SWIN files from DiFX.</description>
      <value></value>
    </param>

    <param type="string" name="OUTPUTIDI" mustexist="false">
      <description>Output FITS-IDI file (or SWIN directory). If equal \nto IDI, the file(s) will be overwritten</description>
      <value></value>
    </param>

    <param type="string" name="DiFXinput" mustexist="false">
      <description>If SWIN files are being converted, this must \nbe the *.input file used by DiFX.</description>
      <value></value>
    </param>


    <param type="any" name="doIF" mustexist="false">
      <description>List of IFs to convert. Default means all.</description>
      <value>[]</value>
    </param>


    <param type="any" name="linAntIdx" mustexist="false">
      <description>List of indices of the linear-polarization \nantennas in the IDI file</description>
      <value>[1]</value>
    </param>

    <param type="any" name="Range" mustexist="false">
      <description>Time range to convert (integer list; AIPS format). \nDefault means all data</description>
      <value>[]</value>
    </param>

    <param type="string" name="ALMAant" mustexist="false">
      <description>If ALMA has been used, this is the antenna table \nfrom the MS with the intra-ALMA visibilities.</description>
      <value></value>
    </param>

    <param type="int" name="spw" mustexist="false">
      <description>Spectral window in ALMAvis that contains the VLBI band. If negative, the program will derive it automatically.</description>
      <value>-1</value>
    </param>

    <param type="string" name="calAPP" mustexist="false">
      <description>If ALMA has been used, this is the combined\nASDM_CALAPPPHASE table from the ASDM.\nThe list of measurement sets can also\nbe given (so the table is\nconcatenated from all of them).</description>
      <value></value>
    </param>


    <param type="any" name="calAPPTime" mustexist="false">
      <description>Time shift and time tolerance (in sec) for the \nCALAPPPHASE table obtained from the ASDM.</description>
      <value>[0.,5.]</value>
    </param>

    <param type="any" name="gains" mustexist="false">
      <description>Gain tables to pre-calibrate the linear-pol VLBI \nstations (one list of gains per linear-pol station).</description>
      <value>[["NONE"]]</value>
    </param>

    <param type="any" name="interpolation" mustexist="false">
      <description> Interpolation type to use (one per calibration table). Tells whether to apply linear or nearest interpolation. Default is to use linear for all tables.</description>
      <value>[]</value>
    </param>


    <param type="any" name="dterms" mustexist="false">
      <description>D-term tables to pre-calibrate the linear-pol VLBI \nstations (one table per linear-pol station).</description>
      <value>["NONE"]</value>
    </param>

    <param type="bool" name="amp_norm" mustexist="false">
      <description>If True, normalize the amplitude correction to the X-Y average, and save the scaling factor (vs time) in an external (ASCII) file. If False, apply the amplitude correction as is.</description>
      <value>True</value>
    </param>

    <param type="any" name="XYadd" mustexist="false">
      <description>Add manually a phase between X and Y before \nconversion (in deg.). One value per linear-pol station.</description>
      <value>[0.0]</value>
    </param>

    <param type="any" name="XYratio" mustexist="false">
      <description>Add manually an amplitude ratio between X and Y before \nconversion (R=X/Y). One value per linear-pol station.</description>
      <value>[1.0]</value>
    </param>


    <param type="any" name="swapXY" mustexist="false">
      <description>Swap X-Y before conversion. One value per linear-pol \nVLBI station.</description>
      <value>[False]</value>
    </param>

    <param type="any" name="swapRL" mustexist="false">
      <description>Swap R-L of the OTHER antenna(s) when plotting\nthe fringes.</description>
      <value>False</value>
    </param>

    <param type="bool" name="IDI_conjugated" mustexist="false">
      <description>Assume a swap in the baseline defintion (i.e., conjugation) of the FITS-IDI file. This has NO effect on SWIN files and shall be set to True. </description>
      <value>True</value>
    </param>

    <param type="any" name="plotIF" mustexist="false">
      <description>IF index(es) to plot. Default means to NOT plot. \nAn empty list, [], means to plot ALL IFs \nbeing converted (but do not forget to \nset plotRange and plotAnt!).</description>
      <value>-1</value>
    </param>


    <param type="any" name="plotRange" mustexist="false">
      <description>Time range to plot (integer list; AIPS format). \nDefault means to NOT plot</description>
      <value>[]</value>
    </param>

    <param type="any" name="plotAnt" mustexist="false">
      <description>Index of the other antenna in the baseline\nto plot. Default means to NOT plot.</description>
      <value>-1</value>
    </param>

    <param type="bool" name="doTest" mustexist="false">
      <description>If true, only compute (and eventually plot), the data,\nbut leave OUTPUTIDI untouched.</description>
      <value>True</value>
    </param>

    <param type="int" name="npix" mustexist="false">
      <description>Number of pixels for the fringe plots.</description>
      <value>50</value>
    </param>



</input>

  <returns type="bool"/>

  <example>

For more information about the internals of PolConvert, please read:

Marti-Vidal et al. 2016, Astronomy and Astrophysics, 587, 143 

PROCEDURE:

Given an FITS-IDI file with phased-ALMA observations, the user must first 
calibrate completely (i.e., in full polarization) the corresponding ALMA 
measurement set. It is important to create it using asis='CALAPPPHASE' in 
the importasdm task. 

If more than one asdm was created in the observations, the user must 
concatenate all the CALAPPPHASE tables of each asdm, for PolConvert to 
work properly. This can be done with the following commands (we assume 
here that MSLIST is a python list with the names of the measurement sets 
for each asdm):

for i,myms in enumerate(MSLIST):
  if i==0:
    os.system('cp -rf %s/ASDM_CALAPPPHASE ./CALAPPPHASE.tab'%myms)
  else:
    tb.open('%s/ASDM_CALAPPPHASE'%myms)
    tb.copyrows('./CALAPPPHASE.tab')
    tb.close()

These lines will create the table './CALAPPPHASE.tab', to be used by 
PolConvert (i.e., the table specified in the 'calAPP' keyword).

PolConvert can also do this for you, if you set calAPP = MSLIST. But
check carefully the information that it will print, regarding the 
time coverage of both the CALAPPPHASE table and the MSs.

Let us assume that the calibration tables are named 'gain.tb' and 
'bandpass.tb' (there can be many others, for delay, XY-phase, etc.) and 
the D-term table is called 'dterms.tb'. Then, with this assumption:

- If ALMA is the only station with linear receivers (let's say it is 
station number 1 in the FITS-IDI file), the call to PolConvert should be 
done with the following keyword values:

- linAntIdx = [1]

- Range = []    # i.e., all data will be converted

- ALMAvis = 'TheALMAvisibilities.ms' 
 
- spw = 0  # it may be a good idea to split first the science spw, 
           # before concatenating and calibrating the ms

- calAPP = './CALAPPPHASE.tab'

- calAPPTime = [0., 5.0]   # The CALAPP entries sometime start and end
                           # with time lags in between. The time tolerance
                           # of 5 seconds should avoid problems related
                           # to this.

- gains = [['gain.tb','bandpass.tb']]
- dterms = ['dterms.tb']

- doTest = False # to actually APLY the changes, not only compute them!


###################
   
     SPECIAL CASE 1:

If there was a second antenna with linear-polarization receivers, 
it can also be converted, but has to be listed after ALMA. Let us assume
that this antenna has id=4 in the FITS-IDI file. Then:

- linAntIdx = [1,4]   # i.e., ALMA plus the other linear-pol. station.

- gains = [ ['gain.tb','bandpass.tb'] , ['NONE'] ]

     # Notice that 'NONE' can be used to tell PolConvert not to apply
     # any calibration.

- dterms = [ 'dterms.dt' , 'NONE']


###################
   
     SPECIAL CASE 2:

If the user wants to check the conversion before applying it, PolConvert
can plot the fringes for a given IF, baseline and time range. Let us 
assume we want to plot the baseline to antenna 2 (i.e., baseline 1-2) in 
the time range 0-07:30:00 to 0-07:31:00 (AIPS format). Then:

- doTest = True  # i.e., do NOT write on the FITS-IDI file!

- plotIF = 1  # i.e., first IF in FITS-IDI file.

- plotRange = [0,7,30,0,0,7,31,0]

- Range = [0,7,30,0,0,7,31,0]  # i.e., to not waste resources computing
                               # things that we will not save nor plot.

- plotAnt = 2  


###################
   
     OTHER SPECIAL CASES (NOT FULLY TESTED):

1.- If two antennas have linear-pol receivers (i.e., ALMA plus another one)
and the second one was correlated with the pol. channels swapped, then:

- swapXY = [False, True]

If it was ALMA the antenna with swapped pol. channels, then:

- swapXY = [True, False]



2.- If the second antenna with linear-pol receivers had an offset of, say,
65 degrees between X and Y, this offset can be corrected before conversion:

- XYadd = [0.0, 65.]


####################################
####################################
##### A TYPICAL DATA REDUCTION #####

1.- Import all ASDMs into measurement sets. 
    BEWARE THAT YOU SET asis='CalAppPhase'

2.- Find out the spw that matches the VLBI frequency setup. Split it for
    each measurement set.

3.- Concatenate the splitted measurement sets. 

4.- Concatenate the 'ASDM_CALAPPPHASE' tables of the measurement sets
    into a new CALAPPPHASE TABLE (see help above).

5.- Calibrate the concatenated measurement set (full-polarization 
    calibration) using standard ALMA procedures.

6.- Execute polconvert, feeding it with the calibration tables and 
    the CALAPPPHASE table, in mode "doTest = True", and applying it
    only to a short (say, 1-2 minutes) scan of a strong source 
    (e.g., the phase calibrator). Select a given IF and antenna 
    to plot (it's better to select a short VLBI baseline to ALMA).

7.- The program will plot the fringes and print an estimate of the 
    extra X/Y phase that should be added to ALMA. This number should 
    be small, as long as the calibration is OK. If a large number 
    is found, and you see large cross-hand polarizations, add this 
    extra X-Y phase to polconvert, via the keyword "XYadd"

8.- Re-execute polconvert in test mode. Check whether the conversion 
    is satisfactory.

9.- Once satisfied with the conversion of the selected calibrator scan, 
    execute polconvert over the shole dataset with "doTest = False".

10.- It may be a good idea to do extra sanity checks, like the 
    possible dependence of XYadd with IF and/or its eventual time 
    evolution. All these effects should have been properly corrected 
    if the measurement set calibration was successful. Different 
    XYadd phases can be added to different IFs by converting each IF
    separately.


# END OF POLCONVERT DOCUMENTATION
#######################################


</example>
</task>

</casaxml>


